bone density is a vital metric when
considering the importance your skeleton
has on daily life I mean unless you move
like the blob from the 1958 horror movie
of the same name your bones are critical
to your health and function not to
mention how debilitating bone breaks can
be later in life as bone density reduces
with age so assuming you want to improve
your bone density and fend off age
related decline what are some sure ways
of doing just that let's find out first
first and foremost is resistance
training resistance training which is
really just any load applied to your
body which your bones tendons and
muscles resist against is probably the
best way to prevent and even
significantly improve bone density in
one analysis including 14 randomized
controlled studies researchers wanted to
know if resistance training could
improve bone mass importantly in older
individuals this demographic that likely
needs it the most if we look at those
data the researchers have all the
studies listed on the left side and then
there's a bunch of Statistics that we
don't need to get into here longtime
physionic subscribers will breathe the
sigh of relief all you need to know is
if the red diamonds move to the right of
the line above zero there's an improved
bone density in the femur and hip and
clearly with all the data together
Illustrated in the very bottom Diamond
there is an effec of resistance training
on bone mineral density I think what's
especially impressive about these data
is that this is in people over the age
of 65 and even into their 70s and Beyond
I mean this is impressive there's a lot
more nuances to that data that I'll get
into in later content but for now we can
say that resistance training improved
bone density so what would be the most
effective exercises though well things
like the most conventional exercise
plans would use so compound exercises so
things like squats dead
overhead press weighted lunges things of
that nature also this can be done using
conventional barbells or it can be used
using dumbbells or even resistance bands
at home oh and one final thing that I
should stress this needs to be done over
many months the analysis had an average
of 43 weeks but some studies lasted up
to 84 weeks which means that some people
continued to train for up to 7 years I'm
not saying that it takes that long but
it'll likely take take at least a year
to notice benefits on the bone itself
although other benefits will come much
sooner the second tip is a supplement in
fact one that I was not aware that had
multiple studies behind it yet doesn't
get discussed much as far as I know on
bone density effects that supplement is
collagen for example this study
researchers gave collagen peptides or
Placebo a non-collagen inert substance
to postmenopausal women for a year and
if we look at that data here we're
looking at a t-core which is a way of
indicating bone mineral density the
higher the bars go the better the blue
bar is the collagen condition clearly it
improved what I find especially
impressive about this is that it shows
pretty significant Improvement of bone
density in women who were not in their
20s and 30s so generally actual acral or
growth of bone is limited to younger
individuals so to see this kind of
improvement in people in their 60s is
pretty impressive we even see further
likely reductions in bone density in the
women who are on Placebo I won't go into
too many more specifics of the study and
while there are some weaknesses of the
study there are also some great
strengths this was even repeated in a
separate study that lasted multiple
years although it too has some
weaknesses all things that I can cover
in a dedicated content for you now we've
covered two tips and we'll cover another
but there is an extended version of this
video that includes more tips for those
that are part of the physionic Insiders
the link is in the description hey plus
you get a ton of additional perks like
premium podcast premium email list
summaries and product recommendations
and more like I said links in the
description now on to tip three the
third tip is actually also a supplement
vitamin D d3s more specifically I did a
in-depth analysis on vitamin D and bone
density a while back looking at these
two analyses across up to 36 studies
vitamin D provided mixed results on bone
density so why am I including it here
well for one there were analyses that
showed Improvement this reads similarly
to the previous one on resistance
training just that the researchers
inexplicably used uh ugly neon green
nothing screams I want to read this like
neon green anyway again the main Diamond
moves to the right indicating
Effectiveness still like I said there's
mixed results and it seems at least
partly to be because there's better
evidence for certain people actually
indicating improved bone density in some
but maybe not in others so who benefits
the people who seem to experience the
greatest benefit were people with low
blood vitamin D as well as those over
the age of 65 also hyperd doing vitamin
D seems to be detrimental to our bones
but that's all explain in this next
video in great detail or if you're more
into other content of mine then check
this out thanks for tuning in
[Music]